Guide to the C.Y. Chu Chinese American trade and immigration documents, 1917-1958 MS 683
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
C.Y. Chu Chinese American photographs, and trade and immigration documents
1917-1971
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Chu, C. Y.
MS 683
2 Linear Feet 1 box
Financial records documenting the career and activities of C. Y. Chu. Also included are C. Y. Chu's 1917 middle school diploma, a 1926 U.S. Dept. of Labor return permit, and more. Photographs of family events and business gatherings.
Biographical / Historical
Chinese American entrepreneur C.Y. Chu opened the Quong Yick grocery store in Houston circa 1930, believed to be the first Chinese-owned grocery in Houston. C.Y Chu went on to help other Chinese start businesses in the U.S., particularly in Houston.
He passed away long before the existence of HAAA. Raymond Gee went through a dumpster at C.Y.'s house after the latter's death and subsequent housecleaning by the latter's brother, and rescued these documents. C.Y.Chu helped lots of Chinese men establish their first grocery businesses when they land in Houston, generously opening his home and helping them set up.
Scope and Contents
Financial records documenting the career and activities of C. Y. Chu. Also included are C. Y. Chu's 1917 middle school diploma, a 1926 U.S. Dept. of Labor return permit, and more.
Photographs of family events and business gatherings. People pictured include C.Y. Chu, Albert Gee, Mr. Parker Gee, Ms. Wanto Chu, Mabel Gee, Mrs. Wing Hon (mother of Judy Gee Chong), Theresa Gee (mother of Rogene Gee Calvert), Helen Gee (wife of Shelton Gee), Shelton Gee, Mamie Gee (wife of Judge Ron Lew, 1st Asian American Federal Judge in the US), and others. Groups include Chinese Baptist Church First Anniversary, Oct. 3, 1954 Chinese Business Men's Dinner, at Timmy Chan Restaurant, Aug. 5, 1956, Houston, TX, unidentified men's dinner group possibly in Albert Gee's Poly-Asian Restaurant, unidentified dinner group at unidentified restaurant.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Raymond Gee via Dr. Anne Chao, 2013.
Index Terms
Subjects
Emigration and immigration; Asian Americans; Chinese Americans; Business; Social life and customs
Document Types
financial records; letters (correspondence); certificates
Places
Texas--Houston
- Series I: Documents, 1917-1958
  - C. Y. Chu middle school diploma, Taishan, Guangdong, Oct. 23, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Canton Christian College letter regarding student Chue Yue Tsoi, Oct. 23, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - U. S. Department of Labor, return permit for C. Y. Chu of San Antonio, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National Bank of Commerce, San Antonio / International Banking Corporation, Hong Kong, China, bills of exchange, $50, payable to C. K. Chu, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hong Kong bills of exchange paid to C. Y. Chu and to China Agency and Trade Co., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Union National Bank Savings Account pass book of Calvin Chu, 1950-1958 (son of C. Y. Chu) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kuo Min Tang of China in America (Chinese Nationalist Party) constitution and interpretation booklet, San Francisco (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - C. Y. Chu business balance sheet calculations, 1940, 1941, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personal letter from elder brother in Canton to C. Y. Chu, Dec. 12, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bank of Canton, San Francisco Branch, Bill of Exchange $50, paid to China Agency and Trading Co., June 19, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal ledger, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kuo Min Tang of China certificate for Chu Gim-Sam (C. Y. Chu), 1925 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal accounting notebook, including names of debtors (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Business ledgers (2) from cash register, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Personal financial record, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Photographs, 1950-1971
  - Family events (19 color snapshots), 1970 and undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Family events (34 color and b/w snapshots), 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Business and church gatherings, circa 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Scope and Contents
    Groups include Chinese Baptist Church First Anniversary, Oct. 3, 1954; Chinese Business Men's Dinner, at Timmy Chan Restaurant, Aug. 5, 1956, Houston, TX; unidentified men's dinner group possibly in Albert Gee's Poly-Asian Restaurant; unidentified dinner group at unidentified restaurant